<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[I am dain]]></title>
  <link href="http://danieldemmel.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://danieldemmel.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-25T17:15:41+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://danieldemmel.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Daniel Demmel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Cross-origin resource sharing with complex jQuery AJAX requests]]></title>
    <link href="http://danieldemmel.me/blog/2013/01/18/getting-cross-origin-resource-sharing-with-complex-jquery-ajax-requests/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-18T17:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://danieldemmel.me/blog/2013/01/18/getting-cross-origin-resource-sharing-with-complex-jquery-ajax-requests</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m working on an HTML5 desktop application which needs to load some HTML text from a server, but not through an existing API. So I had to find a solution which can be set up without too much backend work and make it possible for non-technical people to easily update the content. I&#8217;m assuming that the easiest setup will be using an existing CMS system with a few custom server settings to enable cross-domain communication. It&#8217;s also a security sensitive application, so the content will need to be protected with basic authorisation at least.</p>

<p>Well, let me get things straight: CORS which is more than the simplest GET request is not easy!</p>

<p>While trying to set up and end to end proof of concept to make sure this will work and to be able to advise with setup I ran into several blockers, so I&#8217;m going to go through them step by step.</p>

<h2>Setting up the jQuery AJAX request</h2>

<p>For simple use cases all you need to do to is fire off a simple GET request:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class='highlight'><table><td class='gutter'><pre class='line-numbers'><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='plain'><span class='line'>$.ajax({
</span><span class='line'>  type: 'GET',
</span><span class='line'>  url: 'http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/file/xhr2/',
</span><span class='line'>  success: function(response) {
</span><span class='line'>      var article = $(response).find('article').html();
</span><span class='line'>      $('body').html(article);
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>});</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If the server you&#8217;re hitting is sending back the header <code>Access-Control-Allow-Origin</code> with the value <code>*</code> you&#8217;re all set:</p>

<p><a class="jsbin-embed" href="http://jsbin.com/atobin/1/embed?live,javascript">JS Bin</a><script src="http://static.jsbin.com/js/embed.js"></script></p>

<p>However what I ended up with is far more complicated, as doing anything with custom headers (which included authorisation) you have to first make a so called <a href="http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/cors/#toc-handling-a-not-so-simple-request">preflight</a> request. This is an OPTIONS request which only asks the server if it supports all the headers needed for the &#8216;real&#8217; request which follows.</p>

<p>So let&#8217;s first see the full AJAX request:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class='highlight'><table><td class='gutter'><pre class='line-numbers'><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='plain'><span class='line'>$.ajax({
</span><span class='line'>  type: 'GET',
</span><span class='line'>  url: 'http://www.mydomain.com/myFancyContent.php',
</span><span class='line'>  headers: {
</span><span class='line'>      'MyCustomHeader': 'important information'
</span><span class='line'>  },
</span><span class='line'>  xhrFields: {
</span><span class='line'>      withCredentials: true
</span><span class='line'>  },
</span><span class='line'>  username: 'myuser',
</span><span class='line'>  password: 'mypassword',
</span><span class='line'>  success: function() {
</span><span class='line'>      console.log('success');
</span><span class='line'>  },
</span><span class='line'>  error: function() {
</span><span class='line'>      console.log('failure');
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>});</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>JQuery has some helpers for authorisation, so the easiest way to get it working is setting <code>xhrFields.withCredentials</code> to <code>true</code> and passing <code>username</code> and <code>password</code> as separate parameters, this way we don&#8217;t have to worry about the intricacies of creating the auth hash ourselves.</p>

<p>Another convenience property is <code>headers</code> which you can use to inject any custom headers you might need, without having to manually do it with <code>beforeSend</code>.</p>

<h2>Apache config</h2>

<p>Another big stumbling block for me was to get the settings for Apache right.</p>

<p>The very first thing you need to do is making sure <code>mod_headers</code> is enabled, which can be as simple as:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class='highlight'><table><td class='gutter'><pre class='line-numbers'><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='plain'><span class='line'>$ sudo a2enmod headers
</span><span class='line'>$ sudo /etc/init.d/apache2 force-reload</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Once that&#8217;s done, you can either edit your main <code>httpd.conf</code> or <code>apache.conf</code> files, or just create an <code>.htaccess</code> file in the folder you want to enable CORS in.</p>

<p>These are the settings I ended up with after a lot of experimentation:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class='highlight'><table><td class='gutter'><pre class='line-numbers'><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='plain'><span class='line'>SetEnvIf Origin ^(.*)$ ORIGIN_DOMAIN=$0
</span><span class='line'>&lt;Files "*">
</span><span class='line'>  Header add Access-Control-Allow-Origin %{ORIGIN_DOMAIN}e
</span><span class='line'>  Header add Access-Control-Allow-Methods "GET, OPTIONS"
</span><span class='line'>  Header add Access-Control-Allow-Headers "Authorization, X-Requested-With, Content-Type, Origin, Accept"
</span><span class='line'>  Header add Access-Control-Allow-Credentials "true"
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/Files></span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The first line makes sure that <code>Origin</code> is echoed back, because as it turns out once you have some custom headers a simple <code>*</code> in <code>Access-Control-Allow-Origin</code> won&#8217;t do any more. You can do some URL filtering here if you want, but this setup makes sure that even <code>file:///</code> works which is great for development.</p>

<p>In <code>Access-Control-Allow-Methods</code> we make sure that <code>OPTIONS</code> will work, and with <code>Access-Control-Allow-Headers</code> and <code>Access-Control-Allow-Credentials</code> we set everything up for a basic authorisation handshake.</p>

<p>Annoyingly none of these worked on the simple HTML file I uploaded, until as a desperate idea after a few hours of futile attempts I tried renaming it to PHP extension which made Apache suddenly apply all of them.</p>

<p>If that wasn&#8217;t enough, the unregistered development HTTPS security certificate also blocked my attempts to get things working. If you open any URL on the server you&#8217;re using and accept the certificate this problem will go away, otherwise the options are to <a href="http://superuser.com/questions/27268/how-do-i-disable-the-warning-chrome-gives-if-a-security-certificate-is-not-trust">install / import the certificate on a system level</a> or to start the browser with some flags like <code>--allow-running-insecure-content</code> for Chrome.</p>

<p>Hope this will help someone else facing the same problems!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some thoughts on the fragile relationship between nature conservation and economic growth]]></title>
    <link href="http://danieldemmel.me/blog/2012/09/03/some-thoughts-on-the-fragile-relationship-between-nature-conservation-and-economic-growth/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-03T23:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://danieldemmel.me/blog/2012/09/03/some-thoughts-on-the-fragile-relationship-between-nature-conservation-and-economic-growth</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of the <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/sustain">Sustainability course on Coursera</a> I&#8217;m currently taking, I had to write a forum post around population growth. It was inspired by an article about the dwindling richness of sound recordings in nature and tried to articulate some thoughts around incorporating nature conservation into the economy.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>While human population might be internally sustainable, what about our lasting impact on nature?</strong></p>

<p>Just read an article about Bernie Krause experiencing the shocking loss of biodiversity around the World through audio recordings of wildlife taken a few years apart at the same spots: <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2012/sep/03/bernie-krause-natural-world-recordings">http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2012/sep/03/bernie-krause-natural-world-recordings</a></p>

<p>It&#8217;s crazy how little respect humanity as a whole has towards untouched nature&#8230; Maybe it&#8217;s time for it to be calculated as part of GDP so that land left alone to nature would contribute to this &#8220;sacred index&#8221; which seems to be the only thing which matters in the industrialised world? I wonder what could rein in our relentless colonisation of Earth with our population still set to rise at least for the next few decades.</p>

<p>Unfortunately the UN can&#8217;t force any country to do things differently than its often short-sighted politicians decide under the intoxicating lure of lobby money, maybe the best hope for a source of change could be regional supranational entities like the EU? The pollution / renewable energy generation targets mandated on the EU level are the only thing which I can see that is shaking the political elite into the barest minimum of action here in the UK. While the wealth generated here in London is just staggering, the city fails to meet basic air quality standards already pushed back from a few years ago after repeatedly failing to meet them.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m from Hungary in Eastern Europe originally, and having moved to the UK I&#8217;m really sad to see as I travel in the countryside here that the industrial revolution left precious little wild nature on this island. Maybe it&#8217;s actually a boon that Eastern Europe wasn&#8217;t caught up in such a crazy rate of &#8220;development&#8221; that the really important things are ignored and sacrificed on the altar of &#8220;progress&#8221;. Maybe it&#8217;s because of the agrarian heritage which inevitably comes with a level of respect towards nature?</p>

<p>In the end I guess my main question is: how could it be possible to include nature as part of the wealth of a nation so that capitalism takes notice?</p></blockquote>

<p>It also made me want to grab my sound recorder and go out to capture sounds of nature, maybe even juxtaposed with recordings from the city.</p>

<hr />

<p>Edit: Oh, just after writing this post I found an article which is just about how to value nature as wealth: <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2012/sep/03/ecuador-yasuni-conservation">http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2012/sep/03/ecuador-yasuni-conservation</a></p>

<p>While it starts off really promising&#8230;</p>

<blockquote><p>Just as the species must innovate to survive, Yasuni has inspired the planet&#8217;s most creative and ambitious approach to biodiversity conservation, social development and climate change. Ecuador – which is also home to the Galapagos Islands – is the only country in the world to have recognised the rights of nature in its constitution. After the discovery of a $7.2bn oil reserve inside a pristine corner of the Yasuni national park, the government has proposed leaving the fossil fuel in the ground if the international community will give them half that amount.</p></blockquote>

<p>&#8230;and mentions some interesting numbers and findings&#8230;</p>

<blockquote><p>The UNEP estimates that 40% of the global economy is based on biological products and processes. Biodiversity loss, it says, is becoming a greater concern for businesses than international terrorism.</p></blockquote>

<p>&#8230;apparently the biggest culprits don&#8217;t really care anyway:</p>

<blockquote><p>But what has happened since has been the opposite: because the US, UK and others can consume the assets generated by the amazon jungle for free, they have committed absolutely nothing. The Yasuni ITT initiative has raised a lot less than expected.</p></blockquote>

<p>The sliver of hope though is that while governments don&#8217;t care, people do:</p>

<blockquote><p>The ITT initiative, which covers the Ishpingo, Tambococha and Tiputini oil fields in Yasuni that make up an area of less than one-fifth of Yasuni&#8217;s national park, aims to address this in a core area for protection. Last year, it reached its target of raising $100m thanks to some creative accounting and generous public support (the UK was top for individual donations after featuring in the Guardian), and contributions from Bo Derek, Leonardo DiCaprio, Edward Norton and Al Gore.</p>

<p>Ivonne Baki, who is spearheading the fundraising effort, says the project has now raised $200m, but more is needed. &#8220;The cost of not doing something now will be far higher than the economic crisis. If we are serious about reducing emissions of CO2 and doing something – which is all they talk about at international meetings – then this is the place giving oxygen to the world.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up rmate with Sublime Text for remote file editing over SSH]]></title>
    <link href="http://danieldemmel.me/blog/2012/09/02/setting-up-rmate-with-sublime-text-for-remote-file-editing-over-ssh/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-02T02:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://danieldemmel.me/blog/2012/09/02/setting-up-rmate-with-sublime-text-for-remote-file-editing-over-ssh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you want to be able to edit files using your local Sublime Text 2 app over SSH, you can use <code>rmate</code> which is a small remote connection script developed originally for TextMate.</p>

<p>This is how it goes:</p>

<ol>
<li>Install the <a href="https://github.com/henrikpersson/rsub">rsub</a> plugin for ST2, which is available through <a href="http://wbond.net/sublime_packages/package_control">Package Control</a> too.</li>
<li>Add a remote forwarding line under the right host in your <code>~/.ssh/config</code> file to enable connection: <code>RemoteForward 52698 127.0.0.1:52698</code> – see <a href="https://github.com/henrikpersson/rsub#ssh-tunneling">plugin docs</a> for a bit more info</li>
<li>SSH in to your remote: <code>ssh example_user@123.456.78.90</code></li>
<li>Download rmate: <code>curl https://raw.github.com/aurora/rmate/master/rmate &gt; rmate</code></li>
<li>Move it in place: <code>sudo mv rmate /usr/local/bin</code> – you can put in <code>~/bin</code> too if you only want to set it up for yourself, but sharing is caring :)</li>
<li>Make it executable: <code>sudo chmod +x /usr/local/bin/rmate</code></li>
<li>Profit: <code>rmate .profile</code> – make sure you have an open ST2 window to enable listening!</li>
</ol>


<p>The main reason why I really like this is because you can also <code>sudo rmate</code> with system config files and be able to actually save them back, as opposed to editing via an SFTP client where you need to log in with <code>root</code> to be able to do this.</p>

<p>Also, don&#8217;t forget to open the port in your <code>iptables</code> if you have a restrictive / whitelist firewall policy: <code>-A INPUT -p tcp --dport 52698 -j ACCEPT</code>.</p>

<p>A slightly annoying caveat is that a port can&#8217;t be shared with other people if you happen to be logged in at the same time, so you might have to set up separate ports in <code>iptables</code> with the first port number in the <code>RemoteForward</code> setting matching it (the local port should remain the same). In this case you have to specify the port number in each call though: <code>rmate -p 52699</code>. So probably the best is to create an alias in your <code>.profile</code>: <code>alias rsub='rmate -p 52699'</code>, but in this case you also need to add: <code>alias sudo='sudo '</code>. By adding that trailing space you make sure that the <code>sudo</code>&#8216;d command is also checked for alias substitution, so doing <code>sudo rsub my_system_config_file</code> will still work.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://danieldemmel.me/blog/2012/05/17/setting-up-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-17T22:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://danieldemmel.me/blog/2012/05/17/setting-up-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Steps I&#8217;ve taken</h2>

<p>Note: &#8216;username&#8217; is your Github username and &#8216;myblog&#8217; is the name of your blog / site which you&#8217;ll have to replace in the instructions. Don&#8217;t sweat too much about the latter, it&#8217;s just a project name you won&#8217;t necessary have to use on your site.</p>

<h3>Set up Github repository for hosting</h3>

<p>Go to: https://github.com/new</p>

<p>Fill in form and create repo called &#8220;username.github.com&#8221;</p>

<h3>Set up Octopress <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/setup/">&#8594;</a></h3>

<p>If you don&#8217;t have it yet, install <a href="https://github.com/sstephenson/rbenv#section_2">rbenv</a> and <a href="https://github.com/sstephenson/ruby-build#installing-ruby-build">ruby-build</a> (to handle Ruby runtimes and build gems). If you&#8217;re on Windows this is going to be a bit more complicated, but setting up <a href="http://rubyinstaller.org/downloads">RubyInstaller</a> and <a href="https://github.com/oneclick/rubyinstaller/wiki/Development-Kit">Ruby Development Kit</a> is not that bad.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class='highlight'><table><td class='gutter'><pre class='line-numbers'><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='plain'><span class='line'>$ rbenv install 1.9.2-p290
</span><span class='line'>$ git clone git://github.com/imathis/octopress.git myblog
</span><span class='line'>$ cd myblog
</span><span class='line'>$ gem install bundler
</span><span class='line'>$ rbenv rehash
</span><span class='line'>$ bundle install</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Get a nice theme <a href="http://zespia.tw/Octopress-Theme-Slash/">&#8594;</a></h3>

<figure class='code'><div class='highlight'><table><td class='gutter'><pre class='line-numbers'><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='plain'><span class='line'>$ git clone git://github.com/tommy351/Octopress-Theme-Slash.git .themes/slash
</span><span class='line'>$ rake install['slash']</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Configure Octopress <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/configuring/">&#8594;</a></h3>

<p>Edit at least &#8220;Main Configs&#8221; in _config.yml. You can come back later to fill in the rest.</p>

<h3>Set site up for Github Pages</h3>

<figure class='code'><div class='highlight'><table><td class='gutter'><pre class='line-numbers'><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='plain'><span class='line'>$ rake setup_github_pages</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Paste your Github repo URL: git@github.com:username/username.github.com.git when prompted.</p>

<p>This will set up some folders and the structure of the Git repos. <code>Master</code> branch will track the actual generated website and <code>source</code> will be the sources you are going to edit.</p>

<h3>Create your first post <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/blogging/">&#8594;</a></h3>

<figure class='code'><div class='highlight'><table><td class='gutter'><pre class='line-numbers'><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='plain'><span class='line'>$ rake new_post["Hello World!"]</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Edit contents of myblog/source/_posts/yyyy-mm-dd-hello-world.markdown</p>

<h3>Generate page and see it in your browser <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/github/">&#8594;</a></h3>

<figure class='code'><div class='highlight'><table><td class='gutter'><pre class='line-numbers'><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='plain'><span class='line'>$ rake generate
</span><span class='line'>$ powify create myblog
</span><span class='line'>$ powify browse myblog</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>See if it&#8217;s all good locally</p>

<figure class='code'><div class='highlight'><table><td class='gutter'><pre class='line-numbers'><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='plain'><span class='line'>$ rake deploy</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Check the real thing: http://username.github.com</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[puts 'Hello world']]></title>
    <link href="http://danieldemmel.me/blog/2012/05/17/puts-hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-17T21:48:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://danieldemmel.me/blog/2012/05/17/puts-hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A brave new blog, this time powered by the impressive dream team of <a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org/">Ruby</a>, <a href="http://compass-style.org/">Compass</a>, <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a>, <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> and <a href="https://github.com/">Github</a>.</p>

<p>No database to worry about, back up and restore. Everything is in a Git repository, kindly hosted and served up to the world by Github.</p>

<p>All content is created in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown">Markdown</a>, hand typed in <a href="http://mouapp.com/">Mou.app</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
